Hi everybody, today's דף daf is מ"ב. mem bais. We pick up
on מ"א ע"ב mem aleph amud bais and we are in the
middle of going through the whole issue about מאמר ma'amar after מאמר,
ma'amar, גט get after גט. get. We're basically out of the woods
in terms of some of the most complicated aspects of that, I
know I am always telling you guys that, but anyway, all right.
So,
but what the גמרא Gemara here is doing right now is just
figuring out this issue about why about how this figures into different
issues that we've raised before. So, for example, when רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel says אין מאמר אחר מאמר ואין גט ein ma'amar achar ma'amar
v'ein get after גט, get, the גמרא Gemara says and you person
did let's say
a
חליצה, chalitzah, so he says you know he only follows, excuse me,
the case was he did a גט get to two women,
so according to the חכמים Chachamim he has a problem vis-a-vis the
second woman as well, but also defines his status, according to רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel he can ignore the second co-wife and he just
goes ahead and he does a חליצה chalitzah to the second co-wife.
The גמרא's Gemara only question was how does that fit with שמואל,
Shmuel, because שמואל Shmuel says that if somebody does a גט get
and follows it by a חליצה, chalitzah, it's a weaker חליצה, chalitzah,
it's already been because the זיקה's zika already been weakened and in
that case he has to go ahead and do a חליצה chalitzah
to the other woman as well, and here רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
is saying that even though it's a חליצה chalitzah following a גט,
get, the other woman is totally off. And the גמרא Gemara says
that's because he holds שמואל Shmuel held יש זיקה, yesh zika, so
the גט get weakened the זיקה zika and therefore the חליצה chalitzah
was weaker, but רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel holds אין זיקה. ein zika.
And now the גמרא Gemara says, okay let's assume therefore that the
רבנן Rabbanan hold יש זיקה, yesh zika, so let's pick up with
the top of נ"א ע"ב. nun aleph amud bais. Now there's no
reason because what רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and the רבנן Rabbanan debate
is מאמר אחר מאמר גט אחר גט, ma'amar achar ma'amar get achar
get, but the גמרא Gemara thinks maybe they're also debating this. So
let's say the גמרא Gemara says that רבנן סברי Rabbanan savri very
top of נ"א ע"ב. nun aleph amud bais. רבנן סברי יש זיקה,
Rabbanan savri yesh zika, דקתני סיפא de'tani seifa now let's look at
the end of that, וכן אתה אומר בשני יבמים ויבמה אחת, v'chein
ata omer b'shnei yevamin v'yevama achas, one sister-in-law and two brother-in-laws that
they both went ahead and they gave her a גט get and
then they both and that you have to go ahead and follow
it with a חליצה. chalitzah.
But the חליצה chalitzah says the גמרא Gemara says, so even though
both of the brother-in-laws now are defined vis-a-vis her and also in
the relatives and so on, the act of חליצה chalitzah is only
done by one brother-in-law. Now and that's what the רבנן Rabbanan say.
So now the גמרא Gemara says one minute, how does that work?
לימא תיהוי תיובתא דרב אבא בר אבינא, leima teheve tivta de'Rav Abba
bar Avina, that'll be a challenge on רב אבא בר אבינא. Rav
Abba bar Avina. אמר רב דאמר רב אבא בר אבינא אמר רב
חליצה פסולה צריכה לחזור על כל האחין, amar Rav d'amar Rav Abba
bar Avina amar Rav chalitzah pesula tzricha lachzor al kol ha'achin,
same issue. If you hold יש זיקה, yesh zika, so then the
fact that they both that they gave a גט get and that
a חליצה chalitzah followed a גט get made it a weaker חליצה,
chalitzah, and if it's a weaker חליצה, chalitzah, this חליצה פסולה, chalitzah
pesula, then it's not enough that one brother does it the same
way according to שמואל Shmuel a חליצה פסולה chalitzah pesula doesn't exempt
the co-wife and you have to do a חליצה chalitzah with the
co-wife, similarly a חליצה פסולה, chalitzah pesula, a חליצה chalitzah following a
גט, get, doesn't get the other brothers off the hook and all
the other brothers have to go ahead and give and give and
do a חליצה. chalitzah. So here how come the rabbis say the
other brothers don't have to do a חליצה, chalitzah, again if it's
this weaker חליצה chalitzah it followed a גט? get? So the גמרא
Gemara says אמר לך רב אבא בר אבינא בין מרבן גמליאל ובין
מרבנן סברי אין זיקה. amar lach Rav Abba bar Avina bein me'Rabban
Gamliel u'vein me'Rabbanan savri ein zika. No,
same answer. They both hold אין זיקה. ein zika. So for them
the whole idea that if a חליצה chalitzah follows a גט get
it's a weaker חליצה chalitzah and therefore it has to be done
with all the co-wives and or done by all the brothers, that's
only if you hold יש זיקה, yesh zika, so the act of
giving the גט get weakened the זיקה zika and therefore the חליצה
chalitzah that follows is considered a weaker חליצה. chalitzah. So that's but
he says they don't hold that, they hold אין זיקה ein zika
and therefore the גט get is meaningless, doesn't impact the חליצה chalitzah
that follows and therefore it's not a challenge on us.
Okay, so that's
that. אמר מר, amar mar, let's move on now now we get
to sort of you know something that
again I think is
a
little bit more straightforward. Yes it reminds me again when the
גמרא Gemara says אמר מר amar mar what's
it
going to
do?
It's going back to what we said before to analyze it more
closely.
Okay, a previous אמורא Amoraic statement.
No, this is תנאי, Tannaic, no this is תנא. Tanna. No, the
difference between גופא Gufa and אמר מר Amar Mar is גופא Gufa
is when we quote a line from a Tannaitic source and then
we're going to go bring in the whole text, and but here
we quoted a whole thing and we're looking at it line by
line, piece at a time. אמר מר עשה מאמר בזו ומאמר בזו.
Amar Mar asa ma'amar be-zu u-ma'amar be-zu. So let's say the man
did a מאמר ma'amar with the two co-wives. רבן גמליאל אומר נותן
גט לראשונה וחולץ לה ועושה בקרובותיה. Rabban Gamliel omer noten get la-rishona
ve-choletz la ve-osa bi-krovoteha.
So in that case, again, ignore the second מאמר, ma'amar, focus on
the first one, and therefore if he has to break it off,
he does a גט, get, a גט get counteracting the מאמר, ma'amar,
and does a חליצה, chalitza, ועושה בקרובותיה, ve-osa bi-krovoteha, מותר בקרובות שנייה.
mutar bi-krovot shniya. What he did with the second one is meaningless
and therefore no relationship to her and he's allowed to marry her
relatives, and also right, and he would not do a חליצה chalitza
to her cause why hurt her status? Do a חליצה chalitza to
the first wife where he's already defined the status. Okay, so now
that all makes sense except that if the second מאמר ma'amar was
meaningless, why does he have to break it off with the first
wife? So the גמרא Gemara says מכדי, michti, let's take a look.
קסבר רבן גמליאל אין מאמר אחר מאמר. Kasavar Rabban Gamliel ein ma'amar
achar ma'amar.
The second מאמר ma'amar is meaningless. So ראשונה נמי תיבם. rishona nami
tiyabem. So if that's true, all these cases where you got yourself
into a problem because of the second thing you did and now
you can't finish the first part, now everybody has to get a
גט get and everybody has to get a חליצה, chalitza, that's the
basic thrust here. But according to רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel that the
second one was meaningless and with the first one he did a
מאמר, ma'amar, so just finish it with the first one, go ahead
and do יבום. yibum. That's a reasonable answer.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, גזירה דילמא אתי לייבומי לשנייה. gezeira
dilma ati leyabumi le-shniya.
If we let him follow the מאמר ma'amar with the first one
with a יבום yibum which he really could do because it's a
totally non-problematic status, he might come and say oh, so I did
מאמר ma'amar and then I did יבום, yibum, so the next time
something like this happens, somebody will say I might as well do
the יבום yibum with the second one, and that obviously he would
not be allowed to because then he would already be in a
type of a זיקה zika relationship with the first one and it
would be a case about בית אחד
הוא בונה ואינו בונה שני בתים. bayis echad hu boneh ve-eino boneh
shenei batim. Okay. So again, it's pretty funny because that's like, again,
it's all these questions about are we concerned how much people will
be confused and that would be like a different case, presumably not
this case. This case once he does it with one he's done,
but we don't anyway want to allow it. We want to once
you have it with two, once the two co-wives are involved, we
need to break it off completely even according to רבן גמליאל. Rabban
Gamliel.
But what's the הוה אמינא? havah amina? Why really are they so
concerned, because it's a מאמר ma'amar and not ממש קידושין mamash kedushin
that people get confused? What's the הוה אמינא havah amina to have
a גזירה? gezeira? Why?
No, because because מאמר ma'amar follows יבום yibum and I mean יבום
yibum follows מאמר, ma'amar, and if you have two מאמר-s ma'amar then
you can follow one with יבום, yibum, it's reasonable to assume you
could follow the other one with יבום. yibum. That's a reasonable concern
that somebody will make.
But you have all these sisters-in-law.
No, so right, that's what I'm saying, not in this case that
you'll follow the second one. In some other case just like this,
well the other guy did it with the first, I'll do it
with the second.
אטו? Atu? שמא? Shema?
אטו Atu this case
might lead to something else?
Exactly, which is what makes it a little far-fetched, but okay, bit
of a
גזירה gezeira and you know parallels, it made it so complicated that,
you know, it would be
a lot easier if we just, I'm with you, it would be
a lot easier if we kept the rules clear. Okay. אמר רבי
יוחנן: Amar Rabbi Yochanan: said רבי יוחנן: Rabbi Yochanan: רבן גמליאל ובית
שמאי ורבי שמעון בן עזאי ורבי נחמיה כולהו סבירא להו מאמר קונה.
Rabban Gamliel ve-Beit Shammai ve-Rabbi Shimon ben Azzai ve-Rabbi Nechemia kulu seviru
lehu ma'amar koneh. So all these תנאים Tannaim hold, not the exact
same position, it's gonna be clear here and תוספות Tosafot says it
many times, and we say all these תנאים Tannaim hold the same
position, we mean variations of the same position. Okay, so all these
תנאים Tannaim hold that מאמר ma'amar is קונה קנין גמור, koneh kinyan
gamur, a complete קנין. kinyan. Okay, let's take a look how they
all hold this. So רבן גמליאל: Rabban Gamliel: חד דאמרן. chad de-amran.
רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, that's what we're talking about, that רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel says אין מאמר אחר מאמר. ein ma'amar achar ma'amar. If
אין מאמר אחר מאמר ein ma'amar achar ma'amar means you know, maybe
there's a place for a גט get to be חל, chal, that's
what we talked about yesterday, like two different slots, the מאמר ma'amar
slot and the גט get slot, but within at least the מאמר
ma'amar slot there's nothing left and therefore a מאמר ma'amar that follows
doesn't do anything. בית שמאי דתנן: Beit Shammai de-tnan: שלשה אחים שנים
מהם נשואים שתי אחיות ואחד מופנה. Shelosha achim shenayim mehem nesuim shetei
achayot ve-echad mufneh. So now to a little to see if how
much you remember from before. Three brothers, two of them are married
to two sisters, and one is מופנה, mufneh, one is single. מת
אחד מבעלי אחיות. Met echad mi-ba'alei achayot. One of the guys married
to the sister dies. ועשה בה מופנה מאמר. Ve-asa ba mufneh ma'amar.
And the single guy did a מאמר. ma'amar. ואחר כך מת אחיו.
Ve-achar kach met achiv. And then his brother dies. Okay,
so you might remember this, this is classic, classic whatever for us,
right? You've got
ראובן, Reuven, שמעון, Shimon, לוי. Levi. ראובן Reuven is married to רחל,
Rachel, שמעון Shimon is married to לאה. Leah. Okay. ראובן Reuven dies.
לוי Levi here does מאמר. ma'amar. Already this pen is dying. Okay,
does מאמר. ma'amar. Okay. And then comes and then שמעון Shimon dies.
So now, okay, these are sisters, right, רחל Rachel and לאה. Leah.
So now לוי's Levi a little stuck. Why? Because now he's got
a זיקה zika to לאה, Leah, right, and he's got a זיקה
zika to רחל. Rachel. All right, and
so, and that's the case that the גמרא Gemara has, so if
he goes ahead and
he sort of... consummates one of them, it's like אחות זקוקתו, achos
zikukaso, right? So therefore he has to basically get rid of sort
of to sort of do חליצה chalitza with both. So that's reasonable.
Even without the מאמר maamar you've got the problem, I mean depending
on יש זיקה yesh zika or whatever you got אחות זקוקתו. achos
zikukaso. Comes along בית שמאי Beis Shammai and says no, since he's
already done מאמר maamar with רחל, Rachel, it's like he's already consummated
that. It's like he's already done יבום. yibbum. And לאה Leah just
walks away, so she doesn't even need חליצה. chalitza. It's basically an
ערווה. ervah. So basically the מאמר maamar he already did with רחל
Rachel is like that's a real example even on a דאורייתא de-Oraisa
level, like it's totally already been consummated.
Okay, because now he wants the מאמר maamar to be stronger enabling
לאה Leah to be an ערווה.
ervah. לאה Leah walks away. Right, exactly. Okay, so they say: מת
אחיו והניח אשתו והוא אחיו השני בית שמאי אומרים אשתו עמו. Mes
achiv vehiniach ishto vehu achiv hasheni Beis Shammai omrim ishto imo.
This guy's already married to רחל. Rachel. וזו vezo and the other
one לאה Leah תצא משום אחות אשה tetzei mishum achos isha she
just walks away, completely nothing. Okay, so that's a real case of
מאמר קונה קניין גמור. maamar koneh kinyan gamur. רבי שמעון דתניא. Rabbi
Shimon detanya. אמר לו רבי שמעון לחכמים. Amar lo Rabbi Shimon lachachamim.
So this is a case where two brothers and a sister-in-law and
the two brothers were both were both under Bar Mitzvah. They were
nine years old and a day. So their act of sex was
considered an act of sex, but they were under Bar Mitzvah so
it does not effect יבום. yibbum. And the הלכה halacha is, again
we're going to see this later, that a ביאת קטן bias katan
is considered like a מאמר. maamar. Because you understand the logic, it
quasi does something, it's not enough to be considered a יבום, yibbum,
not an adult, but it quasi does something, it's like a מאמר.
maamar. So let's say both of these under-age brothers basically had sex
with this with their sister-in-law. Okay,
so that's like a מאמר אחר מאמר. maamar achar maamar. What's the
הלכה? halacha? So the חכמים chachamim say well like they both have
to do a גט. get. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, אמר
לו רבי שמעון לחכמים, Amar lo Rabbi Shimon lachachamim, no, אם ביאת
ראשון ביאה, im bias rishon bia, if the first one was meaningful,
ביאת שני אינה ביאה, bias sheni einah bia, then the second one
was not. It's like מאמר אחר מאמר maamar achar maamar which means
it's nothing. This is a straight רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel except applied
to the case of ביאת קטן. bias katan. ואם ביאת ראשון אינה
ביאה ve-im bias rishon einah bia if you don't consider it meaningful
at all, ביאת שני נמי אינה ביאה. bias sheni nami einah bia.
Okay? And therefore he says you don't have to worry about the
second guy. So now the
גמרא Gemara comments: וביאת בן תשע דכמאמר שוויוה רבנן. u-bias ben tesha
de-kimaamar shavyuha rabanan. וקאמר רבי שמעון אינה ביאה veka-amar Rabbi Shimon einah
bia and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you don't have to worry
about the second one. So therefore clearly that shows אין מאמר אחר
מאמר ein maamar achar maamar because אין ביאת קטן אחר ביאת קטן.
ein bias katan achar bias katan. So if we are correct in
assuming that that's equivalent to מאמר, maamar, then it's a similar position
about מאמר. maamar.
Is there such a thing as a גט get from a קטן?
katan?
What? No, no, when it becomes an adult and so on. Okay,
so wait, yeah, yeah, right, exactly, exactly. Okay, whatever, we'll worry about
all that later, but yeah.
Okay, בן עזאי דתניא. Ben Azzai detanya. בן עזאי אומר, Ben Azzai
omer, יש מאמר אחר מאמר בשני יבמין ויבמה אחת. yesh maamar achar
maamar bishnei yevamin veyevamah achas. He says I will admit that if
you have two brothers-in-law and one sister-in-law, the second act of מאמר
maamar is meaningful. Okay, because it's done by...
but ואין מאמר אחר מאמר בשתי יבמות ויבם אחד. ve-ein maamar achar
maamar bishtei yevamos ve-yavam echad. However if you have one brother-in-law and
two sisters, once one guy used up his מאמר maamar for one
woman, he can't use it for another. Now there's a מחלוקת machlokes
רש"י Rashi תוספות Tosafos whether to say it this way or the
reverse. Basically what בן עזאי Ben Azzai is saying is, which one
do you think makes more sense? That there could be a... that
the second מאמר maamar is meaningful if it comes from a second
brother on the same woman, or if it's more likely the second
one is meaningful if it comes from the same brother on a
different woman, on a different co-wife? On
a different wife, right? Because if you think about the קידושין kiddushin
model, right, once a woman is מקודשת mekudeshes it's like done. So
to say you can do מאמר maamar on two different wives, on
two different co-wives, makes more sense than two brothers with the same
woman. Anyway, so רבי שמעון- בן עזאי Rabbi Shimon- Ben Azzai is
saying one of those works, one doesn't. It's a מחלוקת machlokes רש"י
Rashi תוספות Tosafos which what way the גירסא girsa should go. But
we... and so we won't unpack that now. But what we'll notice
is at least in one of those cases, he agrees to רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel of אין מאמר אחר מאמר. ein maamar achar maamar.
Okay, he agrees with one of the cases, either the two wives
or the two brothers, אין מאמר אחר מאמר. ein maamar achar maamar.
בשני יבמין ויבמה אחת, Bishnei yevamin veyevamah achas, that's our גירסא. girsa.
Okay, the question is they they debate who who rewrote the גירסא
girsa and what was the original גירסא. girsa. That's a debate of
רש"י Rashi תוספות. Tosafos.
Okay, רבי נחמיה דתנן. Rabbi Nechemiah ditnan. And רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemiah
that we talked about. רבי נחמיה אומר, Rabbi Nechemiah omer, אחת ביאה
ואחת חליצה בין בתחילה בין באמצע בין בסוף. achas bia ve-achas chalitza
bein batchila bein ba-emtza bein basof. Whether you're doing ביאה bia or
חליצה, chalitza, whether in the beginning, middle or end, אין אחריה כלום.
ein achareiha klum. Afterwards nothing counts. Okay, now we've been teaching that
after חליצה chalitza nothing counts, after ביאה bia it could be a
problem if it's a ביאה פסולה, bias pesulah, right? Well if it's
a ביאה פסולה- bias pesulah no, we saw that even רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel agreed to some of those cases if you remember. Anyway
if it's a ביאה פסולה bias pesulah then something could happen afterwards.
But he says no, even a ביאה, bia, even in the middle,
even if it came after let's say a גט, get, it ends
the whole process. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute: וביאה פסולה
דכמאמר שוויוה רבנן. u-via pesulah de-kimaamar shavyuha rabanan. We've been assuming that
a ביאה פסולה bias pesulah is like מאמר. maamar. וקתני אין אחריה
כלום. vekatani ein achareiha klum. And he says that that ends the
process. So presumably this works within an idea of אין מאמר אחר
מאמר. ein maamar achar maamar. Of course it assumes you buy in
to the idea that ביאה פסולה bias pesulah is equivalent to מאמר.
maamar. And you also might remember that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel himself
said that after ביאה פסולה bias pesulah you could have מאמר, maamar,
you could have something coming afterwards. So again, these are not all
saying exactly the same thing, but they're in a similar type of
an approach that מאמר ma'amar or its
equivalent could cut off the process. Okay, clearly
בית שמאי Beit Shammai is the paradigm of this whole issue about
that מאמר ma'amar is really like it's גמר הדבר. gemar hadavar. Okay,
good. Now we get to move on to today's דף. daf. Not
bad, we're catching up a little bit. כיצד עשה מאמר? keitzad asa
ma'amar? Okay.
So the next of the משנה mishna now goes, after discussing מאמר
ma'amar after מאמר ma'amar and גט get after גט get etc., that
actually if you remember the rest of the משנה mishna goes to
discussing the more hybrid cases. מאמר ma'amar followed by גט, get, מאמר
ma'amar followed by חליצה, chalitza, מאמר ma'amar followed by
ביאה, biya, right? Da-da-da-da-da. גט, get, and then it goes through all
of the hybrids, not all of the pairs, מאמר, ma'amar, מאמר, ma'amar,
גט, get, גט. get. So the גמרא gemara just says, okay, the
משנה mishna isn't reading properly because it says כיצד keitzad and then
it deals with other cases. So the גמרא gemara says, האי גט
אחר גט הוא? hai get achar get hu? This isn't האי גט
אחר גט הוא? hai get achar get hu? Is this a גט
get after גט? get? It speaks about doing a מאמר ma'amar and
then a גט. get. So what do you mean כיצד? keitzad? It's
not כיצד, keitzad, this isn't a גט get after גט, get, this
is a hybrid. So אמר רב יהודה הכי קאמר. amar Rav Yehuda
hachi ka'amar. No, no, no, here's how you have to read it.
גט אחר גט ומאמר אחר מאמר כדאמרן. get achar get uma'amar achar
ma'amar k'damran. The issue of גט get after גט, get, מאמר ma'amar
after מאמר, ma'amar, that's the debate of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and
the חכמים. chachamim. That we've already addressed, where רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
says it's not meaningful and the חכמים chachamim say it is meaningful.
That's a fair debate. Now, how about a hybrid? Oh, in a
hybrid case, everybody agrees that the second one is still meaningful. Right,
even רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel who says אין מאמר אחר מאמר ein
ma'amar achar ma'amar says that there is for example גט get after
מאמר, ma'amar, right? We discussed that yesterday.
יבם אחד ויבמה אחת כיצד? yavam echad viyevama achat keitzad? Now what
are the various, assuming just one brother-in-law and one sister-in-law, what are
the ways in which you can sort of do two stages and
what will be the implications about them? כיצד התרתן? keitzad hitartan? How
would you מתיר matir it once you got yourself into this situation?
עשה מאמר ביבמתו ונתן לה גט צריכה הימנו חליצה. asa ma'amar bivevamto
venatan lah get tzericha heimenu chalitza. You started with a מאמר ma'amar
and then you did a גט, get, then you need a חליצה.
chalitza. Okay? So is that clear? Meaning the משנה mishna first of
all says the basic debate of מאמר ma'amar after מאמר, ma'amar, גט
get after גט, get, that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says no problem,
חכמים chachamim say it is a problem. חליצה אחר חליצה, chalitza achar
chalitza, גט אחר גט, get achar get, everybody says not a problem.
Then it says כיצד. keitzad. כיצד keitzad doesn't really mean כיצד. keitzad.
כיצד keitzad means what's like the whole range of cases? What's the
case of different things? Not מאמר ma'amar after מאמר ma'amar but different
types of things done with one brother-in-law and one sister-in-law and then
we go through the types of ways that he, one person, can
do two things, let's say first a מאמר ma'amar and then a
גט, get, and then how do you go ahead and address it?
Okay. Moving on, עשה מאמר ובעל הרי זו כמצותה. asa ma'amar uva'al
harei zu kemitzvatah.
Now one of the things in גט get as opposed to the
complicated cases that the משנה mishna dealt with of needing to do
a חליצה chalitza and a גט get or two גטין getin and
a חליצה chalitza or one גט get and two חליצות chalitzot or
whatever it was that the משנה mishna was dealing with, those were
all the complicated cases, right? And that was cases everybody agreed because
it wasn't two of the same, it was two different things that
were combined. Then we did have though a case where it actually
worked, where you weren't making it bad, it was good. You did
the logical next step. What are the two cases in which there's
a logical progression? מאמר ma'amar followed by יבום yibum or גט get
followed by חליצה. chalitza. Now גט get followed by חליצה chalitza ironically
we've already heard is a little problematic. It might be called חליצה
פסולה, chalitza pesulah, right? You might have to then do it with
all the brothers and all the wives, that was what we just
discussed earlier, even though logically that's a logical progression, but the גט
get might weaken the זיקה zika therefore problematize the חליצה. chalitza. But
מאמר ma'amar followed by יבום, yibum, that's like normal, that's like קידושין
kidushin followed by נישואין, nisuin, right? So that's the משנה mishna said.
If you had מאמר ma'amar followed by יבום, yibum, that's fine. עשה
מאמר ובעל הרי זו כמצותה. asa ma'amar uva'al harei zu kemitzvatah. So
says the
גמרא, gemara, לימא מסייע ליה לרב הונא? leima mesayei lei leRav Huna?
Let's say this supports רב הונא. Rav Huna. דאמר רב הונא מצות
יבמה מקדש ואחר כך בועל. d'amar Rav Huna mitzvat yevama mekadesh ve'achar
kach bo'el. The מצוה mitzvah of יבום, yibum, the best way, the
right way to do it is first קידושין, kidushin, first מאמר, ma'amar,
and then sex. That parallels how normally קידושין kidushin is done. You
don't just run right into sex, you lay the legal framework first,
and then in that context once you have the קידושין kidushin context
that's when you start having the intimate and the physical relationship. And
that's what you should do even by יבום. yibum. And that would
explain by the way the question became yesterday: why did they create
these institutions of מאמר ma'amar and גט? get? So at least according
to רב הונא Rav Huna you understand they דוקא davka wanted you
to start with מאמר. ma'amar. Don't run in and start having sex.
Is that a way you start a relationship? No, you start by
doing קידושין kidushin and you frame it and you make the commitment
and then within that context then you do the יבום. yibum. Even
though that first stage is דרבנן, derabbanan, that's what the rabbis wanted
you to do.
And continuation of relationship with the brothers and then you could say
that
I understand legally you don't need to, but in
terms of the nature of the actual lived relationship, that's the better
way to do it. Okay, אימא, eima, so the גמרא gemara says,
so what do you mean? So it says, so let's say this
supports him because it says הרי זו כמצותה. harei zu kemitzvatah. Thank
you. So it says הרי זו כמצותה harei zu kemitzvatah sounds like
דוקא davka that's the way you're supposed to do it. So the
גמרא gemara says no, אף זו כמצותה. af zu kemitzvatah. We don't
mean this is the way of doing it properly, it's even this
is appropriate but not that this is the only right way. So
it's a question whether we rule according to רב הונא Rav Huna
that you're really supposed to דוקא davka do it this way or
this is also acceptable.
רמב"ם Rambam rules... What?
It's like a real life I have two ספרים sefarim here for
the דף יומי, Daf Yomi, I don't want to say everything else.
Okay, so anyway, so the רמב״ם Rambam says, here is what the
רמב״ם Rambam says: מדברי סופרים שלא יבוא היבם על יבמתו עד שיקדש
אותה בפני שני עדים בפרוטה או בשווה פרוטה וזה נקרא מאמר.
Midivrei sofrim shelo yavo hayavam al yevamto ad sheyekadesha bifnei shenei eidim
beperutah o beshaveh perutah
vezeh nikra maamar. Okay? ואין המאמר קונה קניין גמור כמו הביאה Vein
hamaamar koneh kinyan gamur kemo habiah etc. etc. Okay. Not exactly clear
to me. Maybe just to emphasize that it's not real קידושין, kiddushin,
but I don't really know. Okay, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this: אימא
אף זו כמצוה aima af zo kemitzvah doesn't prove that's the only
right way to do it, but it's a way to do it,
an acceptable way to do it. But actually רמב״ם Rambam must have
said that it's דוקא davka is the way to do it. פשיטא,
Peshita, obviously it's acceptable to do מאמר maamar and then יבום. yibbum.
Why should that not be acceptable? סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka deitach amina,
I would have thought given that the מאמר... maamar... המאמר העושה מאמר
ביבמתו פרחה הימנו זיקת יבם וחלה עליה זיקת אירוסין, hamaamar haoseh maamar
biyevamto parchah himenu zikat yavam vechalah aleha zikat eirusin, that once somebody
does מאמר, maamar, it's like she's no longer a יבמה yevamah and
we now treat her like an ארוסה arusah ונשואין. venisuin.
So therefore if the מאמר maamar makes it reframes it like it's
no longer a יבמה yevamah context, like it's as if it's a
normal קידושין kiddushin context, אלא לאו מצוה קעביד, ela lav mitzvah kaavid,
then maybe that's not ideal because maybe it's not ideal to reframe
it and make it essentially not no longer like יבום. yibbum. I
mean obviously biblically it is, but if at some rabbinic level now
we're approach it like קידושין kiddushin ונשואין, venisuin, maybe that's inappropriate. Maybe
we should always be approaching it like יבום. yibbum. So קא משמע
לן kamashma lan that no, that that is acceptable even though it
winds up being reframed. By the way, talking about reframing, guess what
the רמב״ם Rambam פוסק, paskens, based on the גמרא Gemara whatever, he
says that you do שבע ברכות. sheva brachot.
Yeah, yeah, isn't that interesting?
So the רמב״ם Rambam says you do שבע ברכות, sheva brachot, so
it's really about re-, you know, looking at it now like a
different type of a thing. I'll read you the רמב״ם: Rambam:
וכשם שהוא מקדש את יבמתו כך הוא מברך ברכת נשואין בעשרה וכותב
כתובה. Ukeshem shehu mekadesh et yevamto kach hu mevarech birkat nisuin baasarah
vechotev ketubah. Okay?
So anyway, so it looks like a regular, it looks exactly.
So maybe I would think that's not ideal, maybe you shouldn't be
reframing it. No, קא משמע לן kamashma lan that it is a
מצוה.
mitzvah. Right. Wow.
גופא, Gufa, let's go back and look at that.
He says you do שבע ברכות sheva brachot after the יבום.
yibbum. Yeah, well no, that's a good question. I mean the רמב״ם
Rambam doesn't exactly say, but normally you do the שבע ברכות, sheva
brachot, you know, before they actually have had sex, you know at
the time of חופה. chuppah.
But there isn't
real, oh the שבע ברכות sheva brachot for the seven days after.
Yeah, it's a good question. I'd have to look into that. Okay.
And because there isn't really a חופה chuppah here, there's just the
sex. Okay, so כיון דאמר מר, kivan deamar mar, so פשיטא. peshita.
Okay so we said גופא, gufa, let's go back and look at
it. אמר רב הונא: Amar Rav Huna: מצות יבם מקדש ואחר כך
בועל. Mitzvat yavam mekadesh veachar kach boel. So the ideal מצוה mitzvah
is first you קידושין kiddushin and then have sex. שאם בא ולא
עשה מאמר קנה. Sheim ba velo asah maamar kanah. However if you
reversed the order, you first had sex and then you did the
קידושין, kiddushin, why you would do the קידושין kiddushin after I don't
know, then it also works. So the גמרא Gemara says: אם בא
ולא עשה מאמר פשיטא, im ba velo asah maamar peshita, that's
קניה בביאה. kaniah beviah. I mean of course that works, I mean
the מאמר maamar afterwards is meaningless, the sex did it. אלא אימא
אם בא בלא מאמר קנה. Ela eima im ba belo maamar kanah.
Okay well that's what he's saying, that he's saying don't get confused
even though I'm telling you that there's a לכתחילה lechat-chila to do
the קידושין kiddushin and then do the ביאה, biah, but if you
did the ביאה biah with even without the קידושין kiddushin at all,
the קידושין kiddushin certainly is not מעכב. meakev.
Okay. והתניא: Veha tanya: one minute the גמרא Gemara says, but we
taught: לוקה מכת מרדות מדרבנן. lokeh makat mardut midrabbanan. If somebody does
the ביאת יבום biat yibbum without the מאמר, maamar, you get lashes.
So that sounds like you're maybe actually still doing an איסור, issur,
maybe חז״ל Chazal aren't recognizing יבום yibbum without... we'll see, but what
the גמרא Gemara at least initially thinks is maybe it indicates that
they're not recognizing יבום yibbum without some context of קידושין. kiddushin. You
have to appreciate how radical this is, right? The תורה Torah basically
says have sex and that does it, and חז״ל Chazal say yeah
but we don't like that. So therefore what we're going to do
is we're going to try to force it into a more acceptable
sort of model, that we socially acceptable, values-based acceptable that we like,
which is that קידושין kiddushin precedes. And now the גמרא's Gemara assuming
that maybe even if you don't do the קידושין kiddushin you get
מלקות, malkus, maybe because it's not even a fully recognized יבום. yibbum.
So the
גמרא Gemara says: והתניא לוקה, veha tanya lokeh, you get מלקות, malkus,
I'm sorry I read too quickly, לוקה, lokeh, you get מלקות, malkus,
maybe even biblical מלקות. malkus. But says no, מכת מרדות מדרבנן. makat
mardut midrabbanan. That's not biblical, that's lashes for being rebellious means you're
violating a rabbinic concern. So biblically obviously it works, but at least
rabbinically we are displeased with יבום yibbum that hasn't preceded קידושין. kiddushin.
Amazing idea, right? You did it exactly like, I mean everybody when
they learn יבמות, Yevamot, you know, so there always talks about like
that it works בעל כרחה, beal korchah, against a woman's will, and
it's so offensive and so on. And obviously those things are, you
know, are really challenged. But on the other hand, you know, here
you have the idea that the rabbis are coming in and they're
basically saying even if both... even if both of the couples want
it, it's inappropriate to do if it's not within a sort of
context of committed relationship, create the קידושין Kiddushin and then go ahead
and do it. And if you do it out of order, even
though it works, you get lashes. Now let's see why you get
lashes. One minute, let's see why you get lashes. To רב, Rav,
מנגיד, mangid, רב Rav would give lashes, rabbinic lashes,
מאן דמקדש בביאה, man de-mikadesh be-via, somebody that basically did קידושין Kiddushin
with ביאה, bia, right? The first, not just יבום, yibum, this is
a general idea. We don't, we want sex to follow the act
of קידושין Kiddushin which frames the relationship. And in that relationship then
you have the act of sex. You don't sort of start it,
and it doesn't start by the physical relationship, it starts by the
commitment and the legal relationship and then sex takes place within that.
So although we learned in the first משנה mishna in קידושין, Kiddushin,
right, כסף שטר וביאה, kesef shtar ve-via, that ביאה bia is an
act of creating קידושין, Kiddushin, not נישואין, nisuin, קידושין, Kiddushin, nevertheless, רב
Rav would give lashes. Even though according to some that's the primary
example of biblical קידושין Kiddushin is ביאה, bia, there's a question which
is the עיקר ikar in the תורה, Torah, ביאה, bia, כסף kesef
etc. Okay, רב Rav nevertheless again very parallel would say I don't
care that you're doing a biblical institution. It's completely unacceptable, you know,
on some moral social plane, and you get lashes. You have to
start with קידושין Kiddushin and then the ביאה bia follows. So he
would do that by קידושין, Kiddushin, he did with the same attitude
by יבום, yibum, who cares that it works דאורייתא? de-oraisa? You have
to follow start it by
קידושין. Kiddushin. ומאן דמקדש בשוקא, u-man de-mikadesh be-shuka, once we're dealing with
giving lashes for people that are doing things that are sort of
social or values-wise unacceptable, somebody that gave כסף קידושין kesef Kiddushin in
the middle of a marketplace.
So like Google, Time Square is out?
Yeah, again, I don't know like most people right, exactly, the people
that get the billboard thing to go up in the middle of
the stadium of the baseball game. I don't, it could be that,
but I think and maybe it's true, maybe it means it's supposed
to be more intimate even the act of, because we're not just
proposing, we're doing the act and it's supposed to be something more
intimate. I also have a sense that it's which I tend to
read the בשוקא be-shuka similar to the next line, which is ומאן
דמקדש בלא שידוכי, u-man de-mikadesh belo shidukhei, you have קידושין Kiddushin without
any engagement process, right? Like שידוכים shidukhim is you know the whole
sort of process leading up and you know and whatever the whole
preparatory courtship. Okay, so and similarly like it's not something
you know you need to the same way you don't start with
the sex within the marriage you start with the קידושין Kiddushin and
then the sex, you don't jump into the marriage. You develop a
relationship or maybe it's the parents develop a relationship depending on how
much it's an arranged or it's between the couple, but nevertheless it's
something that has to be sort of thoughtful and not something that
you do spur of the moment. So that's how I tend to
interpret the שוק shuk problem as well. Oh look, you know, you
know, you don't just סתם stam say hey let's get married, right?
So the שוק shuk sort of suggests something a little impetuous or
not not full without giving it full weight. But it might be
the intimacy aspect as well. Yes.
Well what we read a couple weeks ago about the rabbis marrying
a woman for one day in the שוק. shuk.
There you go.
Well but the question is they didn't do it in the שוק
shuk and they did it with שידוכים shidukhim because they sent ahead
of time and they made a proposal because how do you define
שידוכים? shidukhim? I know it's a good question. It's a good question.
Yes.
In the marketplace. Yes. And you're with a woman in the middle
of the marketplace and you're giving your coins and you say come
with me.
This is
the same rabbi who would have the temporary.
Oh that's a good point. רב Rav said this. It's tying into
רב חסדא, Rav Chizda, it's a good point, this is exactly you're
right I forgot that, that רב Rav was exactly the one who
said מאן להוי ליומא. man le-havei le-yoma. So I don't know what
to do about that. Okay.
It becomes maybe like you know like the same way you would
buy a slave, right?
That the...
oh like being sold in a marketplace. Sold on the sellers block.
Oh. Sense that there isn't really a... well doesn't really imply that
there's no consent on her part because then it wouldn't work anyway.
But it well it depends if the father if she's under age
but it isn't about a personal relationship is what you're saying you
know yeah. So I think all of those are part of this.
Okay.
I think you could get a wife in the marketplace these days
you go to a bar and you hook up with someone.
All right moving on. Okay. ומאן דמקדש בלא שידוכי. u-man de-mikadesh belo
shidukhei. ומאן דנא... u-man de-na... now that's where the קידושין Kiddushin end,
okay, somebody treating it a little too frivolous frivolously at the beginning.
And now we get to people I don't know if I'd say
frivolous but are sort of doing something unethical at the end of
the process as well and mistreating their you know the wife and
maybe again you're right maybe part of this is exactly about too
much objectifying the wife and not seeing her as like a real
you know partner in this. So let's see what the problem is
at the end of the process. ומאן דמבטל גיטא, u-man de-mevatel gita,
right, there's also again גיטין Gittin where a guy sent a גט
get and then he does ביטול bittul without and the שליח shaliach
isn't around and the woman thinks she's divorced and she's not really
divorced.
ומאן דמסר מודעא אגיטא, u-man de-masar moda'a a-gita, and somebody that basically
you know submits a מודעא, moda'a, there's got to be an English
word for this but basically it's something that he declares that the
document that I'm about to sign you should know that I'm you
know I'm not signing it of my free will and therefore it's
not binding. Okay, so somebody submits that that announcement you know before
he goes ahead and does a גט. get. So in the end
the גט get is בטל. batel. Now תוספות Tosafot says in both
of those cases, even if technically those things don't work, for various
reasons they might not work, it doesn't matter because just by doing
them you are making it seem like this woman, you know, isn't
divorced and you're being מוציא לעז, motzi la'az, you're making people suspect
whether she's legitimately divorced or not.
ומן דפקר בשליחותא דרבנן Uman depakar bishluchuta derabbanan and this one doesn't
seem to fit at all
in this context, unless you read it related to a גט. get.
A person that acts, you know, in a rebellious way, in a
defiant way towards a messenger of the court or of even a
rabbi, question if it's דווקא בית דין davka beis din or דרבנן.
derabbanan. ומן דשייא שמתא דרבנן עליה תלתין יומין Uman deshaya shamta derabbanan
alei tlatin yomin ולא אתי לבית דינא ותבע לשמתיה. velo ati lebeis
dina utva leshamtei. Somebody who allowed a נידוי, niduy, right, some type
of this, right, remember the נידוי, niduy, the, we had a good
phrase for it when we did it. Ostracization. Ostracization was a little
harsh, but whatever. Stigma. Some type of a, right, some type of
a rejection or whatever of the rabbis of a mini-ostracization, a mini
חרם cherem that was placed on the person, placed on the person,
and the whole idea was primarily a major use of that of
that שמתא shamta was to get compliance and submission to rabbinic authority
and respect for rabbinic authority. So somebody that has had it placed
on him because of disrespect of rabbinic authority and has been disrespectful
of the contempt, right, that's it, sort of like a charge of
contempt and he's being contemptuous of that because he's going for 30
days and he doesn't care to do anything about that. So that
person רב Rav would also say that's too much and he would
give him lashes. So the last one is about the relationship to,
you know, rabbinic authority, not exactly sure how it fits into the
list. Okay, ועל דתני, ve'al detani, now getting back to sort of
marriage issues, ועל חתנא דדייר בי חמוהי ve'al chatana dedayer bei chamuhi
and a son-in-law that lives in his mother-in-law's
house.
Because then he's with his wife?
No, his wife is there, but you know, his wife goes out
sometimes and he's left possibly alone with his mother-in-law and we're a
little bit concerned about what's going to happen. Is it father-in-law or
mother-in-law?
I don't know, it's a good question.
Father-in-law also goes to work. What? He said it's father-in-law's house. Oh,
חמוהי chamuhi is father-in-law's house? Yeah, I know, I think חמוהי, chamuhi,
I think that might be correct grammatically, but nevertheless even though
it says further on, it says mother, yeah, later on it says,
it's clearly about the concern of the mother-in-law, yeah.
So, but you're right, grammatically it's father-in-law. Okay, דדייר אין דחליף לאו,
dedayer in dechalif lau, only somebody who lives, not somebody that just
is passing by his father-in-law, mother-in-law's house. Okay, like even if he's
like, you know, being a frequent visitor is not a problem, just
living is a problem. So now the גמרא, Gemara, oh but that's
a lead-in to a question, is that really true? וההוא דחליף אבבא
דבי חמוהי, Vahahu dechalif abava devei chamuhi, there's a guy who was
constantly visiting, passing by the door of his father-in-law's house, ונגדיה רב
ששת venagdei Rav Sheshet and רב ששת Rav Sheshet gave him lashes.
So I'll make sure to mention this to my in-laws, we're going
there for Thanksgiving. So the גמרא Gemara says
ההוא מידם הוה דיימי מינה, hahu midam hava daymi mineh, no, that
person was already suspect of having an affair with his mother-in-law, so
therefore given that context and then he was passing by a little
bit too frequently, then he gave him lashes.
Okay, right, exactly. נהרדעי אמרי בכולהו לא מנגיד רב Nahardai amri bekulhu
lo mangid Rav אלא דמקדש בביאה בלא שידוכי. ela demakedesh bevia belo
shiduchi. נהרדעי Nahardai says no, none of this is true, maybe like
in theory he said this, but in practice רב Rav would never
give lashes unless you did two things combined. Number one is you
did קידושין kiddushin with ביאה bi'ah and it wasn't preceded with שידוכין.
shiduchin. So that's really just jumping right into bed, right, there was
no courtship, there was no קידושין, kiddushin, straight to the sex, I
mean sex was the קידושין, kiddushin, but that was the very first
thing. When it was those two combined, that's when he gave lashes.
ואיכא דאמרי אפילו בשידוכי נמי Ve'ika de'amri afilu bishiduchi nami and some
say no, if doing קידושין kiddushin with ביאה bi'ah is a problem
even if it was preceded with a courtship, why? בשידוכי נמי bishiduchi
nami because of
משום פריצותא mishum pritzuta because still it's considered to be licentious, it's
considered to be like too much of a focus on just getting
to the sex as opposed to laying the groundwork first. And again,
that is exactly consistent with the idea of wanting to have מאמר
ma'amar that precedes ייבום yibum rather than even though the ייבום yibum
is exactly the only thing that really is relevant דאורייתא de'oraita and
even perhaps giving lashes to somebody who did exactly what the דאורייתא
de'oraita is if you don't precede it with this rabbinic מאמר. ma'amar.
Yes, Dove.
מידם דיימי Midam daymi means suspect?
Yeah, דומי דמתא, Dumi demata, the word דומי, dumi, yeah, it means
like anyway, it means like suspicion or rumor or whatever. Okay. תנו
רבנן Tanu rabbanan כיצד מאמר? keitzad ma'amar? What is this act of
מאמר? ma'amar? נתן לה כסף או שוה כסף. Natan lah kesef o
shaveh kesef. Fine, like קידושין. kiddushin. רש״י Rashi says that the words
you say
are like הרי את
מקודשת לי harei at mekudeshet li or whatever במאמר יבמין, bemamar yevamin,
like you say something, ואמר לה, ve'amar lah, says רש״י, Rashi, התקדשי
לי במאמר יבמין. hitkadshi li bemamar yevamin. Now the גמרא Gemara doesn't
say that. We'll discuss in a minute, the גמרא Gemara says that
maybe sometimes you might want to frame it a little differently. But
as far as the גמרא Gemara is concerned, I mean the simple
sense of the גמרא, Gemara, you might just say הרי את מקודשת
לי. harei at mekudeshet li. All the גמרא Gemara talks about is
giving... giving the כסף. kesef. It's interesting although מאמר ma'amar might mean
the word, it doesn't tell you what words you say, it just
says you do the כסף. kesef. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
ובשטר כיצד, u-ve-shtar keitzad, so and how would you give a שטר?
shtar? So the גמרא Gemara says בשטר כיצד, be-shtar keitzad, what do
you mean how would you give a שטר? shtar? כדאמרן, ki-de-amran, like
we normally say how you do a שטר קידושין. shtar kiddushin. כתב
לה על הנייר או על החרס, katav lah al ha-niyar o al
ha-cheres, you write on a piece of paper or even on a
piece of pottery, אף על פי שאין בו שווה פרוטה, af al
pi she-ein bo shaveh perutah, even if it's not worth a פרוטה,
perutah, so there's no question that you're not doing קידושי כסף kiddushei
kesef because it's not even worth a פרוטה, perutah, so you write
on this little piece of pottery, what do you write? הרי את
מקודשת לי. Harei at mekudeshet li. So what do you know, there
you go, and that's the language of מקודשת. mekudeshet. The גמרא Gemara
doesn't assume a different language for מאמר. ma'amar. So what do you
mean how you do מאמר? ma'amar? So how do you do שטר?
shtar? So the גמרא Gemara says אמר אביי הכי קאמר, Amar Abaye
hachi ka-amar, this is what we mean, שטר כתובת יבמין כיצד, shtar
ketuvat yevamin keitzad, how you write the כתובה ketubah for יבום? yibum?
Right? Because the כתובה ketubah obligation switched to the brother-in-law. Okay, and
presumably you need to write a new שטר, shtar, which is interesting.
So what do you do? כתב לה אנא פלוני בר פלוני, katav
lah ana ploni bar ploni, I, you know, ראובן בן שמעון, Reuven
ben Shimon, קבלית ית פלונית יבמתי עלי, kabbaleit yat plonit yevamti alai,
I accept the רחל, Rachel, my sister-in-law, upon me, לזון ולפרנסה כראוי,
la-zun u-le-farnesah ke-ra'uy, to feed her and to sustain her as is
appropriate.
So that's the תנאי כתובה, tenai ketubah, that's the ongoing כתובה ketubah
obligation. ובלבד שתהא כתובתה על נכסי בעלה הראשון. u-vilvad she-tehei ketuvatah al
nichsei ba'alah ha-rishon. This presumably is no longer the language of the
כתובה, ketubah, this is a comment of the גמרא, Gemara, but the
actual lien on the property for collecting the כתובה ketubah if she
gets divorced or the guy dies is from her first husband's estate
because again this is some transferring of the relationship. And the גמרא
Gemara says, this is all just repeating stuff we've said before, ואי
לית לה מראשון תקנו לה רבנן משני, ve-i leit lah mi-rishon takkinu
lah rabbanan mi-sheni, but if the first estate does not have the
property to pay for כתובה, ketubah, then she can get it from
the second guy, כדי שלא תהא קלה בעיניו להוציאה, kedei she-lo tehei
kallah be-einav le-hotzi'ah, so he shouldn't figure I can just divorce her
without any consequences. Here there will always be consequences, even if the
first guy didn't have property, it'll come out of his property. Okay,
anyway, that was a digression about כתובה. ketubah.
So תהא קלה להוציאה tehei kallah le-hotzi'ah if he doesn't in the
ordinary case where there's money in the estate?
No, because he would get the brother's estate, so it is in
either way it's coming out of his property, it's just the property
he started with or the property he inherited. Okay, בעי מיניה אביי
מרבה, ba'ei mineih Abaye mi-Rabba, אביי Abaye asked רבה, Rabba, נתן לה
גט ואמר הרי את מגורשת ממני ואי את מותרת לכל אדם מהו.
natan lah get ve-amar Harei at megureshet mimmeni ve-i at mutteret le-chol
adam mahu. Okay, so
now here this is in a יבום yibum case, right? A גט
get of יבום, yibum, what we know what it does is it
פסלס pasuls her on the other brothers, it prevents him from doing
יבום. yibum. What constitutes enough of a rabbinic גט get for יבום
yibum to have that effect? Let's say he said הרי את מגורשת
ממני ואי את מותרת לכל
אדם,
Harei at megureshet mimmeni ve-i at mutteret le-chol
adam, right? Which is like a favorite piece of, it's obviously in
a normal גט get case it would be meaningless, maybe so it's
meaningful enough to create these יבום yibum problems. Okay, so let's take
a look. So what do you say?
So מהו? mahu? גט יבמה דרבנן הוא, get yevama de-rabbanan hu, so
the גט get by a sister-in-law is rabbinic. גט דמהני באשת איש
מהני ביבמה, get de-mahanei be-eishet ish mahanei be-yevama, so maybe we should
say the logical thing is a גט get that works by a
normal case works by a sister-in-law. גט דלא מהני באשת איש לא
מהני ביבמה, get de-lo mahanei be-eishet ish lo mahanei be-yevama, but if
it wouldn't work in a normal case of a marriage, it wouldn't
work to have an impact on the sister-in-law. או דילמא אתי לאחלופי
בגיטא, o dilma ati le-achlufei be-gitta,
it looks close enough like a גט, get, so since it's not
really divorcing her, it's just having all these negative consequences, that'll be
strong enough even if it's not a real גט. get.
Wait, so how do you translate דילמא אתי לאחלופי? dilma ati le-achlufei?
I thought דילמא אתי לאחלופי dilma ati le-achlufei would
be a problem because you'll confuse it with a normal גט, get,
therefore it will have the weight of a normal גט. get. Because,
so the גמרא Gemara says אמרינן חשינא דאתי לאחלופי בגיטא, amrinan chashina
de-ati le-achlufei be-gitta, yeah it looks enough like a normal גט get
and therefore we will give it the weight even though it's not
really good. So מתקיף לה רבה בר חנן, matkif lah Rabba bar
Chanan, so רבה בר חנן Rabba bar Chanan had אלא מעתה יהב
לה ניירא בעלמא הכי נמי דפסלה, ella me-atah yehav lah niyara be-alma
hachi nami de-paslah, like come on, gotta have some standards, oh it
doesn't look good, so let's say he gave her a piece of
paper that had Mary had a little lamb on it and he
said הרי זה גיטך, harei zeh gittech, so would you say אתי
לאחלופי? ati le-achlufei? If it's not a גט, get, it's not a
גט, get, why do you create problems? So the גמרא Gemara says
no, אמר ליה התם לא פסלה בכהונה הכא קא פסלה בכהונה.
amar leih hatam lo
paslah be-khunah hacha ka paslah be-khunah.
Now,
because even in a case of a non-יבום yibum case, we have
an interesting middle category. We have something that's not a גט get
at all and then we have a middle category of a גט
פסול. get pasul. It's enough, it has enough of the qualities of
a גט get that it's called a גט, get, but it's not
valid. What's the relevance of it being a גט פסול get pasul
rather than saying it's not a גט get at all? Is that
if you give a גט פסול get pasul to your wife then
and then let's say this guy and then let's say the guy
dies, the woman would not be an, would be, would be considered
a גרושה gerusha for a כהן. kohen. And she would be if
it's a גט פסול, get pasul, if it's not a גט get
at all, then it was meaningless. But if it was have enough
of the qualities of a גט get even it was invalid, she
would now be, and if the guy who gave it to her
was a כהן, kohen, he couldn't go continue marrying to her, he'd
have to now give her a real גט. get. So a גט
פסול, get pasul, not all גטין פסולים, gittin psulim, but some גטין
פסולים gittin psulim are considered enough have the qualities of a גט
get to rabbinically be meaningful and make her a גרושה, gerusha, rabbinically
a גרושה. gerusha. And if that's true, then it's also meaningful enough
that... That type of a גט get to have the impact on
her as a sister-in-law from the ייבום yibum perspective. So let's read
that. התם לא פסיל בכהונה—blank hatam lo pasil bekhuna piece of paper
you don't invalidate for כהונה. khuna. הכא קא פסיל. hacha ka pasil.
דתניא detanya ואישה גרושה מאישה, veisha gerusha meisha, a woman divorced from
her husband, לא יקחו, lo yikachu, the כהן kohein cannot marry. So
what does it mean divorced from her husband? אפילו לא נתגרשה אלא
מאישה, afilu lo nitgareshah ela meisha, even if she was only divorced
only from her husband and not מותרת muteret to anybody else. הרי
את מגורשת ממני ואי את מותרת לכל אדם. harei at megureshet mimeni
ve-i at muteret le-chol adam. So that's still גרושה מאישה. gerusha meisha.
She's divorced from her husband even though she's not מותרת muteret to
anybody else. Now obviously דאורייתא de-oraisa that has no meaning, this is
an אסמכתא. asmachta. But the אסמכתא asmachta is that is enough to
rabbinically see her as a גרושה gerusha and make her אסור asur
to a כהן. kohein. לא יקחו. lo yikachu. והיינו ריח הגט שפוסל
בכהונה. ve-hainu reiach ha-get she-posel bi-khuna. And that's a concept that the
rabbis call it smells like a גט, get, ריח הגט. reiach ha-get.
So if something has like the smell of a גט, get, it's
enough—it looks like a גט. get. Now then you have an interesting
question. We can go ahead and learn מסכת גיטין masechet gittin and
list a hundred פסולי, psulei, you know, גט פסולים, get psulim, and
we have to figure out which of those have ריח הגט reiach
ha-get and which do not. Which of those enough have the features
that either at the sociological level people perceive as a גט get
or at the הלכה halacha level have enough qualities that make it
a גט get even though it's a גט פסול. get pasul. And
those types of things would actually make the woman אסור asur לכהונה
le-khuna and those things would have the effect of a גט get
in הלכות יבום hilchos yibum as well. Okay, so that's a fascinating
category of ריח הגט reiach ha-get with one of the implications being
הלכות יבום, hilchos yibum, the other being איסור כהונה issur kehuna and
something that is very relevant for when we learn גיטין. gittin.
Do you need to go around a second time and do it
right in הלכות יבום? hilchos yibum?
Well, you mean do it right, a גט get never ends the
process. You still need חליצה.
chalitza. No, I mean if there's cases where you say oh you
need a גט get and whatever it is, if you started with
a מאמר, maamar, you know, whatever it is.
If you did a מאמר maamar and then you did this thing
of a ריח הגט, reiach ha-get, that wouldn't suffice. This is only
enough to create problems, it's not enough to create solutions.
Yeah, but if you committed to give it as a... That invalidates
the גט? get? Correct. So that they're still married?
Yes, but rabbinically it was enough to make her seen as a
גרושה. gerusha. And therefore, if he's a כהן kohein he has to
now really divorce her. Okay.
Or
if the husband dies,
she's אסור asur to a כהן. kohein. Right, so דאורייתא de-oraisa she's
married but rabbinically it had enough traction. Okay. אמר רמי בר חמא
amar rami bar chama הרי אמרו, harei amru, they hold. אמר אחד
ללבלר amar echad le-lavlar somebody said to a סופר: sofer: כתוב גט
לארוסתי, ketov get le-arusati, write a גט get to my ארוסה, arusa,
woman he already did קידושין kiddushin with, לכשאכנסנה אגרשנה, le-che-echansena agar-shenah,
after we have the נישואין nisu'in I plan on divorcing her. Okay?
After after the first night, right, talking about like doing it all
for the sex, then I'm going to divorce her. הרי זה גט
harei zeh get and he wrote the גט get when she was
מאורסת me'ureset before she was נשואה nesua even though he only planned
to give it to her when she was נשואה, nesua, whatever, it's
still a good kosher גט. get. מפני שבידו לגרשה mipnei she-beyado le-garshah
since he could have given it to her right away, you can
give a גט get to a woman you... who's your ארוסה. arusa.
So even though you were planning on waiting till נישואין nisu'in or
whatever, the writing of the גט get is a good writing of
the גט. get. However, ולאישה בעלמא, u-le-ishah be-alma, let's say he said,
"Oh you see that woman over there, רחל? Rachel? I plan on
proposing to her in a week from now and then I'm going
to divorce her. Write a גט get right now." She's not even
my ארוסה arusa right now. And he writes the גט. get. That's
לא חל lo chal because it's writing a גט get for somebody
who isn't my wife when it's being written. Okay?
But is this exactly to get ישן? get yashan?
Oh, so רש"י Rashi תוספות Tosafos discuss that, let's not go there.
You can look at תוספות. Tosafos. ולאישה בעלמא אין גט u-le-ishah be-alma
ein get מפני שאין בידו לגרשה. mipnei she-ein beyado le-garshah. But if
it's a normal woman he's not married to and it's written for
her, it's not a גט. get. Okay, that's background. Now we have
the question. בעי רמי בר חמא. ba-ei rami bar chama. So רמי
בר חמא Rami bar Chama asked—you can see they're having fun, right?
Since we have this idea of a גט get by a יבמה,
yevama, let's bring in הלכות גיטין hilchos gittin and ask what types
of things would... how it would play out. Okay, so ליבמתו מהו.
le-yevamto mahu. Let's say he said, "The guy's brother died, you see
רחל, Rachel, she's my sister-in-law, she's waiting for me to do יבום.
yibum. Write a גט get for her. After I do יבום yibum
I'll give her the גט." get. Is that like an ארוסה arusa
and the גט get is good? Or is that not like an
ארוסה arusa and the גט get is not good?
Okay? She's זיקה zika but... but right now a גט get would
not sever the relationship. A גט get is only meaningful right now
דרבנן, derabbanan, right? So let's take a look. So the question is
מהו. mahu. So now רש"י Rashi says, now what's... what's the question?
Is the question after I do יבום yibum can I give her
the גט get even after I'm דאורייתא de-oraisa married her? The easier
way to understand the question is after I do מאמר. maamar. Remember,
if I do מאמר, maamar, then to release her from the מאמר
maamar I need a גט. get. But that's all at the rabbinic
plane of the מאמר maamar and גט get of a sister-in-law, right?
So we're not yet moving to the דאורייתא de-oraisa that I've done
יבום. yibum. So here's my sister-in-law, write a גט, get, I'm going
to do מאמר maamar and after the מאמר maamar then I'm going
to give her the גט. get. Will that work? Or stay within
the context of sister-in-law before יבום yibum has been done, within the
זיקה מאמר וגט zika maamar ve-get of the rabbinic universe.
Okay, so can that work at the stage of זיקה zika to
give it to her after the מאמר? maamar? That's the question. כיוון
דאגידה ביה keivan de-agidah bei since she's... connected to him, knotted to
him, tied to him, כארסתו דמיא *ka'arusato damya*, she's like the ארוסה
*arusa*, and a גט *get* written now would be good for let's
say after the מאמר ma'amar *maamar*. או דילמא כיון דלא עבד בה
מאמר *o dilma keivan de'lo avad bah maamar*, since he hasn't yet
done the מאמר *maamar*, no, there's no real relationship yet. It's not
even like an ארוסה *arusa* and a גט *get* is meaningless. תיקו
*teiku*, we don't know the answer. Okay. בעא רב חנינא *Ba'ei Rav
Chanina*. So רב חנינא *Rav Chanina* asked: כתב גט לזיקתו ולא למאמרו
למאמרו ולא לזיקתו *katav get lezikato velo lemaamaro lemaamaro velo lezikato*. A
guy went ahead and he did מאמר *maamar* with his sister-in-law and
then he said, "I am writing a גט *get* to free you
from the מאמר *maamar* act that I've done but not from the
זיקה zika *zikah*." Or, "I'm writing a מאמר *maamar* to free you
from the זיקה zika, *zikah* but not from the מאמר *maamar*." Okay,
can you write a גט *get*? Now obviously even if you try
to write a גט *get* for the זיקה *zikah*, it still needs
חליצה chalitza *chalitza*. But at least rabbinically that's meaningful because if the
גט *get* attacks the זיקה *zikah*, that means that now I can't
do יבום yibum. *yibbum* anymore, right? פסלה *pasla*. Maybe the other brothers
can't either because I've attacked the זיקה *zikah*. But what I said
is, so but I said is now I'm going to only attack
the זיקה *zikah* but not the מאמר *maamar*, only the מאמר *maamar*
and not the זיקה *zikah*. Is that like trying to divorce my
wife halfway and it's maybe completely meaningless? And therefore maybe the גט
*get* has absolutely no impact because she has a double status and
I'm trying to address only half of her relationship, my relationship to
her.
We saw yesterday that you can marry half the woman.
Okay, right. So this is no different. So תיקו *teiku*. So בעא
רב חנינא *Ba'ei Rav Chanina*: כתב גט לזיקתו ולא למאמרו למאמרו ולא
לזיקתו מאי *katav get lezikato velo lemaamaro lemaamaro velo lezikato mai*? What
do we say? מאמר עילויי זיקה קרמי *maamar illuyey zika karami*. The
מאמר *maamar* is on top of the זיקה *zikah*. The זיקה *zikah*
is the base relationship and now that you build the מאמר *maamar*.
והוי ליה כמגרש חצי אשה *v'havay lei k'migaresh chatzi isha*. It's like
I tried to divorce half of a woman, right? I tried to
sever half my relationship without the other half. המגרש חצי אשה לא
עשה ולא כלום *hamigaresh chatzi isha lo asa velo klum*. And therefore
it's meaningless and the גט *get* does not affect her status at
all and maybe I could even do יבום yibum *yibbum* afterwards. It's
like the גט *get* was meaningless. או דילמא האי לחוד והאי לחוד
*o dilma hai lachud v'hai lachud*? Or do we say each thing,
the זיקה *zikah* and the מאמר *maamar*, are independent and even if
I attack one, if I do a גט *get* against one, it
works for that part and therefore it's a meaningful גט *get* and
it has all of its consequences. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says:
ותפשוט ליה מדרבא *vitifshot lei mi-deRava*. Why not learn it from רבא
*Rava*? דאמר רבא *de-amar Rava*: נתן גט למאמרו הותרה צרתה *natan get
le-maamaro hutra tzarata*. That basically a person did a מאמר *maamar* to
one of the co-wives and
that then implicated the other co-wife, you can imagine some of the
scenarios. And then רבא *Rava* says: okay, but if you did a
גט *get* to remove the מאמר *maamar*, you're back to square one.
So what we see from רבא *Rava*'s case is that you could
do a גט *get* just on the מאמר *maamar part, not on
the זיקה *zikah* part. All right? I mean you don't have to
worry about the specifics of רבא *Rava*, but you get the idea.
A guy did a מאמר *maamar*, if he does a גט *get*,
the גט *get* can remove the מאמר *maamar* that he did and
it frees up the co-wife and it gets you back to square
one. So you see a גט *get* can work just on the
מאמר *maamar*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says: לרבא פשיטא ליה לרב חנינא
מיבעיא ליה *l'Rava peshita lei l'Rav Chanina mibaya lei*. For רבא *Rava*
it was obvious that at least you could do a גט *get*
just on the מאמר *maamar*. Whether you could do a גט *get*
just on the זיקה *zikah* maybe is more
questionable, right? That you could do a גט *get* on the top
layer without the bottom is more obvious that you could do a
גט *get* on the bottom layer without the top. But anyway, at
least for רבא *Rava* you could do a גט *get* just on
the מאמר *maamar*. But רב חנינא *Rav Chanina* doesn't know. And so
מאי *mai*, what's the הלכה halacha *halacha*? תיקו *teiku*. Again, we don't
know either. So can you have a גט *get* just for half
of the equation and will it be meaningful enough to therefore have
the implications of a גט *get* or will it be like a
joke, you know, completely meaningless? We don't know the answer to that.
Okay. That was, I gotta admit that that was a little bit
more fun or understandable than the stuff that preceded it. Okay, so
חלץ ואחר כך מאמר *chalatz v'achar maamar*. Now we get to the
idea that אין אחר חליצה כלום *ein achar chalitza
klum*. Okay. So the guy went ahead and he did חליצה *chalitza*
to one wife. Now, if he did a מאמר *maamar* after he
did חליצה *chalitza*, what has he just done? Here it is: his
brother died, he's got שרה *Sarah* and רבקה *Rivkah* there. He goes
ahead, he does חליצה *chalitza* to שרה *Sarah*. Then he does מאמר
*maamar*, either the שרה *Sarah* or the רבקה *Rivkah*. What has he
just right now done? He's done nothing. No, what is מאמר *maamar*
right now? Isn't an act of קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin*? So he basically
has tried to do קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin* to a woman that is
his חלוצה *chalutza*. Now what's the how assur is she to him?
Now you might say, "Oh well, it's now אשת אח *eshet ach*,
it's איסור כרת *issur kares*." But if you remember, we don't say
that. We say the status is a new לאו *lav* called כיון
שלא בנה שוב לא יבנה *keivan shelo bana shuv lo yivneh*. Since
he did חליצה *chalitza* now he doesn't have the option again to
marry her again, but it's a simple לאו *lav*. If he would
have married רבקה *Rivkah*, the one he did חליצה *chalitza* to, and
has sex with her, he would just be over on the לאו
*lav* of אשר לא יבנה *asher lo yivneh*. So it's an איסור
לאו *issur lav*. So why does the משנה *Mishnah* say he did
חליצה *chalitza* then מאמר *maamar* lo אין אחר חליצה כלום *ein achar
chalitza klum*, לא עשה ולא כלום *lo asa velo klum*? Right, what
do you mean? It's just an איסור לאו *issur lav*. Why isn't
that a binding קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin*? Right, is that clear? This woman
is a woman he did חליצה *chalitza* to, now he did קידושין
kiddushin *kiddushin* with, that should be binding, it's an איסור לאו *issur
lav*.
Why don't we say she's now reverting to אשת אח *eshet ach*?
We don't because based on the פסוק *pasuk* we learn out that
there's a new status. That was an earlier גמרא *Gemara*. There's a
question whether the co-wife... might be אשת אח *Eshet Ach*, but she's
just the איסור *Issur* of שוב לא יבנה *Shuv Lo Yivne*. So
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב *Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav*, זו דברי
רבי Rebbi. עקיבא *zu divrei Rabbi Akiva*. This is the words of
רבי Rebbi עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* that the מאמר *Ma'amar* is meaningless. ואמר
אין קידושין kiddushin? תופסין בחייבי לאוין *Ve'amar ein kiddushin topsin be'chayei lavin*
because she's an איסור לאו *issur lav*, קידושין *kiddushin* isn't binding. אבל
חכמים אומרים יש אחר חליצה כלום *Aval chachamim omrim yesh achar chalitzah
klum*, that no, after חליצה *chalitzah* if you did a מאמר *ma'amar*
that actually would be a קידושין *kiddushin*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says
ומי מצית מוקמת לה כרבי עקיבא *u-mi matzit mookamita k'Rabbi Akiva*, how
could you say it's רבי Rebbi. עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*? והקתני רישא נתן
גט ועשה מאמר צריכה גט וחליצה *Ve'aktani reisha natan get ve'asah ma'amar
tzricha get ve'chalitzah*. The beginning said that if he gave a גט
*get* and then he followed it with a מאמר *ma'amar*, so now
he needs a גט *get* for the מאמר *ma'amar* and a חליצה
*chalitzah* because you need a חליצה *chalitzah*. ואי רבי Rebbi עקיבא כיון
דיהב לה גט מה מהני בה מאמר *V'ee Rabbi Akiva kivan de'yahav
lah get mai mahani bah ma'amar*? But according to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi
Akiva*, if you started with a גט *get*, why would the מאמר
*ma'amar* be meaningful? והתניא רבי עקיבא אומר מניין לנותן גט ליבמתו שנאסרה
עליו עולמית *Ve'ha tanyah Rabbi Akiva omer minayin lenosen get leyivimto she'neasrah
alav olamit*? How do you know once you give a גט *get*
to your sister-in-law, you're done? שנאמר לא יוכל בעלה הראשון אשר שלחה
*Shene'emar lo yuchal ba'alah harishon asher shilchah*, this is not by a
sister-in-law, this is by a normal wife, the first husband who sent
her away should not, cannot go ahead and remarry her. אחר שלוח
*Achar shiluach*, once she's sent away, he can't be remarried. Now what's
he saying that's not in the פסוק *pasuk*? Because the פסוק *pasuk*
says after a man divorces his wife and she goes ahead and
has sex with another man, marries another man, he can't remarry her.
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* is ending it by saying no, he cannot
remarry her אשר שלחה *asher shilchah* that just by sending her away
he can't remarry her. So there's some case in the תורה *Torah*
where immediately after divorce he can't remarry even if she doesn't marry
another man. Of course it could be a כהן *kohen* and a
גרושה *gerushah*, but we already know that. So what's the case? The
case must be giving a גט *get* to your sister-in-law, and once
you sent her away, she's done. So the גמרא *Gemara* thinks that
that's דאורייתא *de'oraita* according to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*. Now that's again
fascinating. I want to remind ourselves, we've been assuming that מאמר *ma'amar*
and גט *get* by a sister-in-law is all דרבנן *de'rabbanan*. But remember,
בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* has מאמר *ma'amar* is דאורייתא *de'oraita*, and Leah
gets totally off in this case. She's דאורייתא *de'oraita*. Here it sounds
like רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* holds that גט *get* is דאורייתא *de'oraita*.
Maybe she still needs to do a חליצה *chalitzah*, he's not saying
you don't have to do חליצה *chalitzah*. But certainly that the fact
that מאמר *ma'amar* makes גט *get* makes her forbidden to now do
יבום *yibbum* and makes maybe the other wives forbidden, that it sounds
like is דאורייתא *de'oraita*. So if that's דאורייתא *de'oraita*, so how can
he say that there's a מאמר *ma'amar* after גט *get*? You're back
to square one. If she's אסורה *asurah* to him דאורייתא *de'oraita* after
the גט *get*, it's the same as after חליצה *chalitzah*. That if
there's an איסור דאורייתא *issur de'oraita*, the מאמר *ma'amar* afterwards should not
work. אמר אביי Abaye *amar Abaye*, no, גט יבמי מדרבנן *get yavni
mi'de'rabbanan*, don't take that דרשה *drasha* too seriously. A גט *get* is
only rabbinic. וקרא אסמכתא בעלמא *V'kra asmachta be'alma* and the verse is
just a support. So after a גט *get* it's only rabbinic, so
מאמר *ma'amar* would be effective afterwards. Whereas after חליצה *chalitzah*, that's a
דאורייתא *de'oraita* she's forbidden to him and according to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi
Akiva* that there's no קידושין *kiddushin* by חייבי לאוין *chayei lavin*, so
therefore it does not take effect after חליצה *chalitzah* but it does
take effect after גט *get*. Is that clear? We have a thing
that it sounds like גט *get* is דאורייתא *de'oraita*, so if it
doesn't take effect after חליצה *chalitzah* shouldn't take effect after גט *get*
if there's no קידושין *kiddushin* once a woman is even a simple
לאו *lav*? And the answer is no, even though it sounds like
it's דאורייתא *de'oraita*, גט *get* is only דרבנן *de'rabbanan*. So therefore מאמר
*ma'amar* will take effect, but after חליצה *chalitzah* it will not.
This גט *get*, a גט *get* of a יבמה *yevama*.
Right. תניא נמי הכי ותירצמי אמר רבי אין הדברים הללו אמורים אלא
לדברי רבי עקיבא *Tanya nami hachi ve-tirtzemai amar Rabbi ein hadvarim halalu
amurim ela ledivrei Rabbi Akiva*, רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, שהיה עושה חלוצה
כערוה *shehaya oseh chalutzah ke-ervah*, that he would make a חלוצה *chalutzah*
like an ערוה *ervah*, he would make every איסור לאו *issur lav*
like an ערוה *ervah*. אבל חכמים אומרים יש אחר חליצה כלום *Aval
chachamim omrim yesh achar chalitzah klum*, even after חליצה *chalitzah*, if you
do a מאמר *ma'amar*, it's קידושין *kiddushin* and therefore it's binding. ואני
אומר *Va'ani omer*, now רבי *Rabbi* says, but I say אימתי *eimatai*,
when is this true that there's that you can do מאמר *ma'amar*
after חליצה *chalitzah*? בזמן שקידשה לשום אישות *Bizman she-kidshah leshum ishous*, what
did you say? Remember what confused you, what tricked you all, was
we used the word מאמר *ma'amar*. So he says, what did you
do after חליצה *chalitzah*? Did you say הרי את מקודשת לי harei
at mekudeshet li, *harei at mekudeshet lee* simple? Then it's קידושין *kiddushin*
and then it's binding. אבל קידשה לשום יבמות *Aval kidshah leshum yavmus*,
if you said הרי את יבמתי *harei at yivmanti* or הרי את
מקודשת לי במאמר יבמין harei at mekudeshet li b'ma'amar yavmim *harei at
mekudeshet lee be-ma'amar yevmin* or something like that and you were trying
to do it as a יבום *yibbum* type of an act, in
that case אין אחר חליצה כלום *ein achar chalitzah klum*, then you're
only within the rabbinic מאמר *ma'amar*, you're not doing a real קידושין
*kiddushin* and then it wouldn't work. So now for the first time
we are seeing that if you introduce a concept of יבום *yibbum*
in the language of the מאמר *ma'amar*, you really might reframe it
as not a classic קידושין *kiddushin* and it would not be binding.
תניא אידך *Tanya idach*, we'll do one more, we taught in a
ברייתא *Baraisa*, החולץ ליבמתו וחזר וקידשה *hacholetz leyivimto ve-chazar ve-kidshah*, same my
dear, חליצה *chalitzah* and then and then קידושין *kiddushin*. רבי אומר *Rabbi
omer*, so this is the רבי *Rabbi* who distinguished between what you
said, אם קידשה לשום אישות צריכה הימנו גט לשום יבמות אין צריכה
הימנו גט *im kidshah leshum ishous tzricha mimenu get leshum yavmus ein
tzricha mimenu get*. It depends how you said it. Normal קידושין *kiddushin*,
it's חל *chal*. יבום *yibbum* קידושין *kiddushin*, not חל *chal*. וחכמים אומרים
בין שקידשה לשום אישות בין שקידשה לשום יבמות צריכה הימנו גט *Ve-chachamim
omrim bein she-kidshah leshum ishous bein she-kidshah leshum yavmus tzricha mimenu get*.
It doesn't matter. You still said הרי את מקודשת לי harei at
mekudeshet li. *harei at mekudeshet lee*, I don't care what other words
you said. That's going to be binding. אמר רב יוסף *Amar Rav
Yosef*, said רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*, מאי טעמא דרבי *mai ta'ama de-Rabbi*?
Why does רבי *Rabbi*... say that when you say it's לשם יבום
it doesn't work? You still said הרי את מקודשת. harei at mekudeshet.
So, אציעא דאודא בנכסי הגר וכסבר שלו הן דלא קני. atzu'a t'uda
b'nichsei hager v'kasavar shelohen d'lo kani.
It's like somebody was, now you gotta try to deal with the
analogy here, plowing in the yard of a גר. ger. So a
גר ger is a convert. Why do we say גר? ger? Because
if a גר ger dies and he has no heirs, any Jew
who naturally born Jew who dies, somebody's going to be their heir,
some other Jew who's somehow related. But if a convert dies, there
are no heirs, so the land is הפקר. hefker. And the first
person to do חזקה, chazaka, to do work in the land, is
קונה koneh it. Let's say you're working in the land, but you
didn't realize that it belonged to a גר ger who died, you
thought it was your yard. So, are you קונה koneh or not?
So the הלכה halacha is דלא קני, d'lo kani, you're not קונה.
koneh. So here too, you did an act of קידושין with this
woman, but you didn't realize you were doing an act of קידושין,
you thought you were acting doing an act of קידושי יבמין. kiddushei
yavmim. And there, right? You said הרי את מקודשת לי harei at
mekudeshet li. במאמר יבמין yavmim or whatever. Had you done an act
of קידושין, it would have worked. Like if the guy had plowed
in the field of the גר ger knowing he was trying to
be קונה, koneh, it would have worked. But he was doing it
as a different thing, and therefore it didn't work. So that's the
analogy. That's why it doesn't work for רבי. So אמר ליה אביי,
amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said to him, מי דמי? mi
dami? What type of comparison is that? התם לא קמכוין למקני. hatam
lo k'michaven l'mikni. In the case by the גר, ger, he just
thought he was plowing his own yard. You weren't trying to do
a קנין kinyan at all. הכא קמכוין למקני. hacha k'michaven l'mikni. You're
trying to do a קנין. kinyan. You're just trying to do a
קנין kinyan of יבמין yavmim and that doesn't work, but a קנין
kinyan of קידושין would work. So it's not a good analogy. הא
לא דמי, ha lo dami, if you want an analogy, here is
the analogy: אלא עודר בנכסי גר זה וכסבר של גר אחר הוא.
ela oder b'nichsei ger zeh v'kasavar shel ger acher hu. You were
plowing in this yard, you thought that it belonged to a certain
גר ger who died, and actually it belonged to a different גר
ger who died. So what do you think the הלכה would be?
You're still trying to be
קונה koneh it. וקני. v'kani. And here too, if you're trying to
be מקדש mekadesh this woman, even if you're trying to do it
as an act of יבום קידושין, yibum kiddushin, you're still trying to
be מקדש mekadesh her. It should still work. So why according to
רבי does it not work? אלא אמר אביי, ela amar Abaye, so
last line, so אביי Abaye says, here's why it doesn't work according
to רבי. הכא במאי עסקינן כגון דאמר לה התקדשי לי במאמר יבמין.
hacha b'mai askinan kegon d'amar lah hitkadshi li b'ma'amar yavmim.
Because I actually had introduced the idea before. The גמרא until now
thought it was just what was going on in your head. You
actually said הרי את מקודשת לי, but in your head you were
thinking you're doing it for יבום. So then אביי says, why shouldn't
it work? Who cares what's going on in your head? You said
הרי את מקודשת לי. What do I care whether you're thinking this
גר ger or that גר, ger, for יבום or קידושין? You're saying
הרי את מקודשת לי. So the answer is the only way to
explain רבי why it doesn't work is that you actually said words
that framed it differently. Okay? You said הכא במאי עסקינן דאמר לה
התקדשי לי במאמר יבמין. hacha b'mai askinan d'amar lah hitkadshi li b'ma'amar
yavmim. רבי סבר מאמר עילוי זיקה קא רמי, Rebbi savar ma'amar illui
zika ka rami,
that the מאמר that's going building on the זיקה because you're saying
יבמין yavmim it has to work in a יבמין yavmim context. והא
חליצה אפסקה לזיקה, v'ha chalitza afsaka l'zika, and the חליצה broke it,
so you can't be working in a יבמין context anymore. ורבנן סברי
האי לחודיה קאי והאי לחודיה קאי. v'rabbanan savri hai l'chudei kai v'hai
l'chudei kai.
Okay, each one is by itself, and that even without the זיקה,
if you're saying התקדשי לי, hitkadshi li, even though you're saying as
a יבום קידושין, yibum kiddushin, you're still saying התקדשי לי hitkadshi li
and it still works. All right, we will end here.